Elisha Kent Kane Papers 1810-1973 1843-1857 Mss.B.K132
American Philosophical Society
Elisha Kent Kane Papers
Bulk, 1843-1857
1810-1953
Mss.B.K132
American Philosophical Society
6.75 Linear feet
The most stellar member of a stellar family, Elisha Kent Kane was among the most popular American explorers of the mid-nineteenth century, a hero in the tragic mode. Born in Philadelphia in 1820, the son of John Kintzing Kane and Jane Duval Leiper, Kane studied medicine at the University of Pennsylvania before earning a commission as a naval surgeon. While in the Navy, Kane embarked on the succession of voyages to exotic locales that became the basis for his extraordinary fame. In 1843, he attended Caleb Cushing's first diplomatic mission to China as ship's physician, and subsequently traveled to the Philippines and Western Africa. Distinguishing himself in the Mexican War, Kane's greatest fame came from two expeditions to the arctic, aiming to locate the lost explorer, Sir John Franklin and to explore for evidence of the open polar sea. Kane died in 1857 while attempting to organize a third arctic voyage. Part of the Kane Family Collection, the Papers of Elisha Kent Kane contain a mix of personal and family correspondence with correspondence relating to all of Kane's explorations. Intelligent, articulate and very much a romantic, Kane's letters are expressive and passionate. The collection provides fine documentation of youth, his relationship with the Spiritualist Margaret Fox, and of course his travels to China and off the coast of Africa in 1846. Kane's two expeditions to the arctic are particularly well documented, with correspondence, notes, logbooks, diaries, and sketches, as well as Kane's post-expedition notes, writings, and lectures recounting his experiences.
Kane, Elisha Kent, 1820-1857
Bibliography
Corner, George W., Dr. Kane of the Arctic Seas (Philadelphia: Temple Univ., 1972). Call no.: B K132c.
Elder, William, Biography of Elisha Kent Kane (Philadelphia: Childs and Peterson, 1858). Call no.: B K132e.
The Love-Life of Dr. Kane: Containing the Correspondence, and a History of the Acquaintance, Engagement, and Secret Marriage Between Elisha K. Kane and Margaret Fox (New York: Carleton, 1866). Call no.: B K132f.
Sawin, Mark Horst, "Raising Kane: The Creation and Consequences of Fame in Antebellum America" (Dissertation, University of Texas, Austin, 2001).
African American History Note
Among the most popular of American explorers of the mid-nineteenth century, Kane visited Africa in 1846 aboard the frigate United States. The Kane collection contains a variety of fascinating materials relating to the slave trade and plight of African Americans in the nineteenth century.
The papers consist of manuscript materials entitled " Journal of a Trip to Africa," " Slave voyage notebook," and " Whydah slave trade." Also, there are two " Africa: miscellaneous" folders which include an essay on the commercial policy and history of the Gold Coast, along with quantitative data for the years 1820-1843 regarding the repatriation of African Americans to Liberia.
Naval History Note
The diverse Kane Papers include the arctic explorer's correspondence, sketches of arctic and other scenes (there are many sketches scattered throughout the numerous bound volumes), notebooks of polar exploration, journals of trips to North Carolina, the Philippines, Africa, the Near East, Egypt, Mexico, logbooks, etc.
The logbooks are catalogued separately and can be viewed at: Kane Logbooks (Mss.B.K132a).
The Kane papers also include printed materials which may be of interest to naval historians. Printed sources include:
Great Britain. Admiralty. "By the commissioners for executing the office of Lord High Admiral of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland, etc. ...To Horatio T. Austin, Esq., C.B., captain of Her Majesty's Ship 'Resolute,' in charge of an expedition to the Arctic Sea." 1850. 3 pages.
Ross, Sir James Clark. "Aston Abbotts House, Aylesbury. 18th February, 1853. Sir, With respect to the number of each party, we have found two officers and six men to be the most convenient." 1853. 2 pages.
Richardson, Sir John. "From Sir John Richardson, C.B., Medical Inspector, on equipment for Arctic travelling. Haslar Hospital, Feb. 14th, 1853. In pursuance of the commands of My Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty, conveyed in your letter of the 12th instant, that I should make such remarks and suggestions, as my experience in Arctic travelling may enable me to do, for the information of Dr. Kane, of the United States Navy, appointed to the command of an expedition." 1853. 3 pages.
Great Britain. Admiralty. "H. M. S. _____ __th of _____ 18__ Lat. _____ Long._____ _____ Commander...Whoever finds this paper is requested to forward it to the Secretary of the Admiralty, London, with a note of the time and place at which it was found." 18__. 1 page.
Godfrey, William C. "History of the Grinnell Exploring Expedition to the Arctic Ocean, in search of Sir John Franklin, 1853-4-5. Dr. E. K. Kane, U.S.N., commanding. By William Godfrey, one of the survivors of the expedition." Circa 1857. 1 page.
Maryland Institute. "Memorial. To the Honorable the Senate and House of Representatives of the United States, in Congress assembled: The undersigned memorialists, members of the Maryland Institute and citizens of Baltimore generally...pray that an expedition of recovery be fitted out...[to search for Sir John Franklin and the lost crews of the Erebus and Terror]." n.d. 1 page.
Parry, Sir William Edward. "Northbrook House, Bishop's Waltham, Feb. 16th, 1853. Sir, In reply to your letter of the llth Inst. (receive only to day, I hasten to assure you how much pleasure it would afford me to contribute, in any degree, to the efficiency of Dr. Kane's equipment in the arduous enterprize in which he is about to be engaged." 1853. 1 page.
Meriam, Ebenezer. "The Franklin lifesaving and Arctic exploring expedition. The brilliant effort now making by Henry Grinnell...for the early departure of an expedition which he is fitting out for the Polar Seas, from his own private fortune, for the search and rescue of those who embarked in the exploring expedition which sailed from England under the command of Sir John Franklin, is worthy of every aid and facility which can be extended to so noble and praiseworthy an undertaking." 1850. 2 pages.
Sabine, Sir Edward. "Woolwich, February 24, 1853. Sir, With reference to the letter which you addressed to me on the 12th of February, in respect to Dr. Kane's Arctic Expedition, I must limit the suggestions...to...'magnetic observations'." 1853. 1 page.
Early American History Note
This large collection contains the papers of Elisha Kent Kane, a prominent Philadelphian who led the U.S. Exploring Expedition. The collection is well-described and inventoried in MOLE.
Separated Materials note
Several items associated with Elisha Kent Kane have been transferred to the APS Curatorial Department for storage.
Buttons from Elisha Kent Kane's U.S. Naval Attire, early 19th c.Brass
Pocket Watch, Duchene Brothers and Co., 19th c. Said to have belonged to Elisha Kent Kane
Medal with Portrait of Elisha Kent Kane, 19th c.
Ceremonial Sword, Nathan P Ames, Springfield, Mass., ca. 1843, Presented to Kane by the U.S. government
The APS owns an oil portrait of Kane by James Reid Lambdin, after an ambrotype by Mathew Brady, 1857.
Related Archival Materials note
The Elisha Kent Kane Papers are part of the Kane Family Collection (Ms. Coll. 115), which includes materials for John Kintzing Kane, Robert Patterson Kane, Thomas Leiper Kane, and Francis Fisher Kane and Eliza Middleton Kane Cope. Several of these contain material relevant to Elisha Kent Kane.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of Mrs. Joseph C. Aub, Dr. Oliver Cope, Thomas Pym Cope, Mrs. Thomas P. Hazard, Mrs. E. Paul DuPont, 1967-1973 (accn no. 1970-145ms, 1973-1615ms); and purchase.
Arrangement note
Series I. Correspondence 1810-1953 (bulk: 5.5 linear feet
Series II. Financial Records 1831-1861 0.25 linear feet
Series III. George W. Corner, Notes on Elisha Kent Kane 1854-1973 0.25 linear feet
Series IV. Bound Volumes 1835-1860 1.5 linear feet
Series V. Graphics ca.1840-1856 0.25 linear feet
Scope and Contents note
Part of the Kane Family Collection, the Elisha Kent Kane Papers is comprised primarily of correspondence written by the naval officer and explorer, Elisha Kent Kane, between 1840 and 1857. In addition to a thorough run of letters documenting his intricate and occasionally scandalous personal life, the collection includes a wealth of material regarding Kane's claim to fame: his expeditions to China, Africa, Mexico, and the Arctic.
An erudite family, the Kanes wrote letters that were warm, beautifully penned and highly descriptive, and from the time of Elisha's departure from home to attend school through his varied missions abroad, they offer intimate glimpses of family life and local news in Philadelphia. Similarly, Elisha's letters home describe a student's life in fine detail, and recount both his adventures in exotic locales and his dreary ship-bound days with equal aplomb. From early in his career, Elisha was very image conscious, and the entire Kane family was deeply involved in creating and preserving his image and reputation. The letters he wrote home were often edited and forwarded to the newspapers for publication.
Perhaps no aspect of Kane's life is better documented in the collection than his participation in the two Grinnell expeditions to the arctic, 1850-1851, and 1853-1854. These include not only correspondence with supporters of the project but also copies of Kane's diary, logbooks, notes, and sketches, along with drafts of some of his later writings. Among these are a full suite of meteorological readings from 1850-1851, interesting descriptions of the "eskimeaux" and their way of life, and drafts of Kane's journal from December 1856, when his deserting crew returned to the Advance.
Kane's tumultuous love life is both well documented and frustratingly sparse. His brief affair with Julia Reed is whispered in a small number of documents, perhaps most clearly in a contract drawn up between unnamed parties for an unmarried woman to surrender her child to be raised by the father. The very public affair with the Spiritualist medium Maggie Fox is discussed in an extensive series of letters and documents, though questions about the nature of the relationship still remain unanswered. Several historians have suggested that Kane initially seemed fascinated by Fox's skills as a spiritualist, but that as the relationship advanced, he implored Fox to give up her "rapping" and to pursue a more honest lifestyle. She eventually agreed to attend school and allowed Kane to place her with a family in Crookville, Pennsylvania. Perhaps Kane felt his family might be more accepting of Fox once she had received an education.
The Fox-Kane correspondence includes letters to and from Maggie Fox, and her sisters Kate and Leah and mother Margaret, asking for Kane's support. In at least some cases, the letters appear to have been gathered together by Robert Patterson Kane, presumably as the family prepared itself to defend Elisha's public reputation.
Other travel-related correspondence includes some fascinating translations of letters from Antonio Gonzalez and a Mr. Ferrer "concerning the treatment of free negroes in Cuba." A long letter from "the house of Gen. Gaona" dated February 10, 1848, to his father describes his host's generosity and hospitality.
The remaining series of the Kane Papers consist of personal financial records (Series II), material collected by George Corner when preparing his biography of Kane (Series III), and graphic materials (Series V).
Biographical/Historical note
Whether because of -- or in spite of -- a debilitating childhood bout with rheumatic fever that left him with a delicate constitution, Elisha Kent Kane went on to live an adventurous life and "die in the harness," as his father had wished. Each of the half-dozen brilliant forays that he made into the exotic seems to have been terminated by accident or illness, but from these experiences, Kane carefully built a public image for himself as America's great tragic hero of exploration.
Elisha Kent Kane was born in Philadelphia on February 3, 1820, the son of the jurist and Democratic politician John Kintzing Kane and his wife Jane Duval Leiper. Already prominent in Philadelphia and Washington, the Kane family became more so with Elisha's celebrity as an Arctic explorer and his brother, Thomas Leiper Kane's, as a general in the Union army and advocate for the Mormons.
Upon first entering college at the University of Virginia, Elisha intended to study geology and civil engineering, but on the advice of family friends, he transferred to the University of Pennsylvania to take up medicine, graduating in 1842. With receipt of his degree, however, his concerned family members believed that a medical practice might be too rigorous for the frail young man, and they sought to discourage him from the profession. But unbeknownst to Elisha, his father arranged a surgeon's commission in the navy, and upon graduation, Elisha was directed to report to the Philadelphia Navy Yard to be examined for assignment. Despite his medical history, Kane passed the examination and received his commission in the following year.
In his first assignment, Kane joined the diplomat Caleb Cushing on the first American diplomatic mission to China in May 1843. The voyage to the Far East was the first of many adventures for Kane, which included a daring descent into a Philippine volcano, apparently inciting controversy among locals. At the completion of trade negotiations in June 1844, Kane resigned from the Cushing Commission and elected to remain in China for six months, operating a hospital boat with a young English surgeon. Although the venture was successful financially, Kane contracted cholera and was forced to abandon his practice and return home. By the time that he reached Philadelphia in the summer of 1845, he had logged thousands of miles and visited five continents.
Despite his stated intentions of settling down and opening a medical practice in the city, Kane soon enlisted for another tour of duty at sea, this time taking a cruise to Africa aboard the frigate United States. It has been suggested that Kane's precipitous decision to ship out had less to do with a thirst for adventure than it did a taste of scandal. Shortly after his return to Philadelphia Kane had begun spending time with a young woman named Julia Reed, and several months later, he was scurrying to conceal her pregnancy. While historian and Kane biographer George W. Corner acknowledged that there was some correspondence to support the basis for the scandal, he nevertheless maintained that an out of wedlock pregnancy "did not fit" Kane's gentlemanly character. Regardless of the circumstances, however, sail away Kane did in May 1846, leaving behind a despondent family and two heartbroken cousins, Mary Leiper and Helen Patterson. Although Kane did not appear to enjoy his African sojourn, it afforded him the opportunity to study the slave trade at first hand, a topic of great interest to the Kane family, and especially to his abolitionist brother Thomas and to his father.
Just as in China, however, illness cut short Kane's cruise, and he returned home weak, emaciated, and depressed, and just as in China, he was not held back for long. Even before he had recovered from his bout of "coast fever," he traveled to Washington to petition for a transfer into the army in order to fight in the Mexican War. The prospects of escape and adventure and of military glory were always supremely attractive to Kane, but after contracting yet another debilitating illness, he gave up hope of active duty. Failing in his attempt to sign on as physician to Girard College, he renewed his push for a transfer, and when President James Polk decided he needed a messenger to relay information to General Winfield Scott, Kane was offered the assignment.
En route to Mexico, Kane wrote to his father to assure him that the "Philadelphia Kane family is represented in the war," and he challenged him to use this "representation" to further advance the Kane family. Ultimately, Kane's stint in the army did bring credit to his family's name. Wounded in a battle with Mexican forces, Kane distinguished himself by saving the life of Mexican General Antonio Gaona, and in return, Gaona and his family nursed Kane back to health in their luxurious compound after the illness-prone Philadelphian had fallen ill with "congestive typhus fever." Declared unfit for further duty, Kane was sent home to a hero's welcome.
After a slow convalescence over the summer, Kane unsuccessfully applied for a position at the Philadelphia Navy Yard, and then for an assignment aboard the store ship Supply, scheduled to sail for Lisbon, the Mediterranean, and Rio de Janeiro. Reminiscent in many ways of Kane's African trip, the Supply cruise was uneventful apart from the brutal floggings meted out frequently on the backs of the unruly crew that Kane, as ship's surgeon, was obligated to attend. In September 1849, Kane left his assignment aboard the Supply, and signed on aboard the surveying steamer Walker, bound for Mobile Bay on coastguard service.
While the experience aboard the Supply deepened Kane's aversion to shipboard brutality, he found his coastguard duty irredeemably dull. Kane yearned for adventure, and early in the following year, the perfect opportunity presented itself: a rescue expedition was forming to search for the lost explorer Sir John Franklin, who had last been seen on July 22, 1845 en route to locate a Northwest Passage to the Pacific Ocean.
On May 22, 1850, Kane set sail aboard the brig Advance, one of two ships supplied for the expedition by the whaling magnate Henry Grinnell. The U.S. Navy crew under the command of Lieutenant Edwin De Haven, was charged with searching for Franklin in Baffin Bay, but he was ordered thereafter to proceed northward in search of the still undiscovered Northwest Passage. There were ten other rescue ships in the Arctic that summer. Between August 25th and 27th, the crews of Captain John Penny and De Haven landed on the shores of Cape Riley where they discovered evidence of an encampment, presumably Franklin's, and additional evidence was discovered on Beechey Island, ten miles further up Wellington Channel. Since Franklin had left no indication of the direction in which he was headed, the captains agreed to split up and continue their search over a wider area, with De Haven heading north up Wellington Channel.
In early September, the Advance passed Cornwallis Island and began heading further north before it was stopped altogether by a howling storm. Scrubbing the mission, De Haven elected to try to return home, but as ice formed around the ships and locked them into a floe, they found themselves trapped, and pushed steadily northward. Even when the floe broke up temporarily, the ship was freed only long enough to become frozen into another icepack headed south. By October 1st, Kane and his shipmates realized that they faced a winter in the Arctic.
In the dark and bitterly cold winter, De Haven and many in the crew became desperately ill with scurvy, leaving their health and survival in Dr. Kane's hands. Ordering them to exercise, even on the coldest days, and increasing their rations, Kane is credited with saving their lives. After having been pushed out of Wellington Channel, eastward through Lancaster Sound, and southward down Baffin Bay, the ship was finally freed of the ice on June 5, 1851, and was able to make its way to Greenland's Disco Island to replenish stores for another season of exploration.
From Upernavik, the expedition set sail again in early July and soon after hit solid ice. By mid-August, the frustrated De Haven abandoned the mission and headed for New York before facing another arctic winter. Although they had failed to locate Franklin or the Northwest Passage, when Kane returned home, he was once again received as a hero.
Making the most of the acclaim, Kane spent the next year traveling and lecturing on his Arctic adventures to capacity crowds. His celebrity grew enormously as a result of his colorful lectures, and carefully edited accounts of his Arctic adventures filled the newspapers. Perhaps most famously, he worked tirelessly to promote his theory that Franklin had drifted into a warm-water Open Polar Sea that he was sure circled the pole. Using the attention resulting from his book, The U. S. Grinnell Expedition in Search of Sir John Franklin, Kane raised funds for a second expedition, taking the largest share from the magnanimous Henry Grinnell, who agreed to once again offered use of the Advance. It appeared as though Kane would have every opportunity to test his theory.
The fall of 1852 was marked by two significant events: the tragic death of fourteen year-old Willie Kane and the introduction of Elisha Kent Kane to Margaret Fox, one the best known Spiritualist mediums in America. Willie's death devastated the entire family, so much so that they abandoned their mansion on the outskirts of Philadelphia and moved back into the city, unable to bear living in Willie's house any longer. Elisha, who had kept watch at Willie's bedside for several weeks, was particularly affected. There has been some speculation that Kane's grief led him to seek out the comfort of Spiritualist communication with the dead; however, there is no evidence that Kane ever actually discussed Willie with Maggie Fox. Nevertheless, after several visits to the hotel where Fox held seances, Kane's spirits improved, and as he labored to finish his book and to complete organization for his expedition, he continued to pay regular visits.
Although their relationship started out casually, Kane began to make demands on Fox. Initially unconcerned over the propriety of her "calling," he soon began to urge her to give it up, and at the same time, he began to insist that she become more ladylike, proposing that she allow him to send her to school. For her part, Fox seemed uncertain whether she would comply or resist, but as their relationship grew more intense, the demands became more important. At one point, Kane broke off the relationship, recognizing that one of them would have to give up their "cause," something that neither was willing to do.
Fox must have had a change of heart, because a few months later she wrote to Kane expressing dissatisfaction with her "very tiresome life" and asking his advice. His immediate reply encouraged her to "stick to your good resolutions" and reaffirmed his commitment to helping her escape a life which, according to Kane, was "worse than tedious, it is sinful." Maggie's mother finally agreed to allow Kane to arrange for Maggie's education, and the Turner family of rural Crookville, Pennsylvania, was engaged to provide board for Maggie while she attended school nearby. Kane also made arrangements with Cornelius Grinnell to pay her board and take care of other incidental expenses. The young couple agreed that if Kane was sufficiently satisfied with Fox's reeducation when he returned from the Arctic, they would be married, but until then they could not become engaged. On May 27, 1853, Fox moved into the Turner's home in Crookville, and four days later Kane departed for the Arctic.